Tobacco label collection (Library of Congress)
Prints & Photographs Division, Library of Congress
Tobacco label collection ca. 1844-1890 bulk 1861-1887
LOT 10618
ca. 900 prints: engravings, etchings, lithographs, b&w and color, 35 x 43 cm. or smaller
Prints & Photographs Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
These labels and advertisements for tobacco reflect varied aspects of American history, popular culture, and politics of the nineteenth century.
For information about Prints and Photographs Division collections and services, see the Prints & Photographs Division's Reading Room Home Page.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
Subjects
African Americans--1840-1890.; Animals--1840-1890.; Children--1840-1890.; Courtship--1840-1890.; Emblems--1840-1890.; Entertainers--1840-1890.; Entertainment--1840-1890.; Events--1840-1890.; Fictitious characters--1840-1890.; Flags--1840-1890.; Indians of North America--1840-1890.; Love--1840-1890.; Sports--1840-1890.; Supernatural beings--1840-1890.; Theatrical productions--1840-1890.; Tobacco industry--1840-1890.; Women--1840-1890.
Places
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Military personnel.
Form/Genre
Engravings--1840-1890.; Etchings--1840-1890.; Genre prints--1840-1890.; Humorous pictures--1840-1890.; Lithographs--1840-1890.; Portrait prints--1840-1890.; Tobacco package labels--1840-1890.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Copyright deposit; 1840-1890.
Additional form available
Digitized images of some items in the collection and their associated identifying information are available through the Prints & Photographs Online Catalog, by searching using the call number "LOT 10618."
Scope and Content Note
Images reflect varied aspects of American history, popular culture, and politics of the nineteenth century. Examples of topics depicted include African-Americans, animals, children, Civil War generals, events, flags, gods & goddesses, humorous situations, Indians, literary characters, people, smoking, portraits of American and European political figures, sports, symbols, the theater and theatrical personalities, the tobacco industry, and women.
Organized/Arranged
Sorted into eighty-three subject categories. Subject arrangement covers events (listed chronologically), portraits, and general topics (alphabetical).
http://lccn.loc.gov/2002696082
Container List
- Discovery & exploration, 4 items; LOT 10618-1
- War (portraits, Declaration of Ind.), 1775-1881, 5 items; LOT 10618-2
- War, 1812, 1 item; LOT 10618-3
- War (Mexican), 1846-1848, 4 items; LOT 10618-4
- War (Civil), 1861-1865, 13 items; LOT 10618-5
- War (Union and Confederate generals), 1861-1865, 11 items; LOT 10618-6
- Views, U.S., (2 folders) 30 items; LOT 10618-7
- New York State (Seals, symbols, etc.), 6 items; LOT 10618-8
- Cuba, 4 items; LOT 10618-9
- Europe, (2 folders) 32 items; LOT 10618-10
- Japan & Japanese, 6 items; LOT 10618-11
- Near East & Turkey, 21 items; LOT 10618-12
- Views, foreign, 3 items; LOT 10618-13
- U.S. Presidents, 4 items; LOT 10618-14
- Garibaldi, Giuseppe, 4 items; LOT 10618-15
- Jackson, Thomas Jonathan (Stonewall), 2 items; LOT 10618-16
- Lee, Robert E., 5 items; LOT 10618-17
- Acrobats, 2 items; LOT 10618-18
- African Americans, 14 items; LOT 10618-61
- Agriculture & farming, 4 items; LOT 10618-19
- Allegories, 9 items; LOT 10618-20
- Amazons, 3 items; LOT 10618-21
- Angelic figures, 4 items; LOT 10618-22
- Animals, 29 items; LOT 10618-23
- Animals (comic), 4 items; LOT 10618-24
- Atlantic Cable, 3 items; LOT 10618-25
- Balloons, 1 item; LOT 10618-26
- Baseball, 4 items; LOT 10618-27
- Beehives, 2 items; LOT 10618-28
- Biblical illustrations, 2 items; LOT 10618-29
- Bicycles & bicycling, 14 items; LOT 10618-30
- Birds & amphibians, 7 items; LOT 10618-31
- Birds (comic), 2 items; LOT 10618-32
- Boxing, 4 items; LOT 10618-33
- Cavaliers, 2 items; LOT 10618-34
- Children, 14 items; LOT 10618-35
- Christmas, 1 item; LOT 10618-36
- Daily life & activities, 27 items; LOT 10618-37
- Dancers & dancing, 10 items; LOT 10618-38
- Fashions, 6 items; LOT 10618-39
- Flags, patriotic symbols, eagles, U.S., 26 items; LOT 10618-40
- Flowers, 7 items; LOT 10618-41
- Foreign trade, 1 item; LOT 10618-42
- Fraternal organizations (Concordia Mannerchor), 1 item; LOT 10618-43
- Fruit (includes one engraving on wood), 7 items; LOT 10618-44
- Horses & horse racing, (2 folders) 18 items; LOT 10618-45
- Humor, 14 items; LOT 10618-46
- Hunting & fishing, 7 items; LOT 10618-47
- Indians & Indian life, (2 folders) 25 items; LOT 10618-48
- Industry, business, manufacture, 4 items; LOT 10618-49
- Justice, 3 items; LOT 10618-50
- Knickerbocker, Diedrich (fictional character), 3 items; LOT 10618-51
- Knights & crusaders, 7 items; LOT 10618-52
- Literary characters & authors, (2 folders) 20 items; LOT 10618-53
- Locks & keys, 1 item; LOT 10618-54
- Love & courtship, 14 items; LOT 10618-55
- Portraits, Men, (2 folders) 22 items; LOT 10618-56
- Military organizations, 7 items; LOT 10618-57
- Monks, 2 items; LOT 10618-58
- Mythology (Gods & goddesses), (3 folders) 32 items; LOT 10618-59
- Navy, U.S., 5 items; LOT 10618-60
- Nudes, (2 folders) 23 items; LOT 10618-62
- Organ (Great Organ Tobacco), 1 item; LOT 10618-63
- Pioneer west, 10 items; LOT 10618-64
- Politics, 2 items; LOT 10618-65
- Portraits, (2 folders) 27 items; LOT 10618-66
- Railroads, 4 items; LOT 10618-67
- Roman life & times, 3 items; LOT 10618-68
- Seals & emblems, (2 folders) 26 items; LOT 10618-69
- Ships (clipper & steam), 2 folders; 21 items; LOT 10618-70
- Smoking, (2 folders) 31 items; LOT 10618-71
- Sports (General), 7 items; LOT 10618-72
- Theater & theatrical personalities, 21 items; LOT 10618-73
- Tobacco labels (text), (2 folders) 27 items; LOT 10618-74
- Tobacco (leaf, growing, shipping), 10 items; LOT 10618-75
- Tobacco (manufacture, retailing), 6 items; LOT 10618-76
- Tobacco currency, 1 item; LOT 10618-77
- Women (sentimental portraits), (5 folders) 101 items; LOT 10618-78
- Zouaves, 1 item; LOT 10618-79
- Tobacco labels (miscellany), (2 folders) 29 items; LOT 10618-80
- Eclipse, 1 item; LOT 10618-81
- Far East, 2 items; LOT 10618-82
- Fenian movement, 2 items; LOT 10618-83